If it's really inconvenient for you,
您要是实在不方便的话
we can talk here.
我们就可以在这儿聊
It won't take long.
耽误不了多长时间的
Captain Wei,
我们第一次见面
don't you think it's
魏队长不觉得
a bit abrupt for our first meeting?
这样实在太唐突了吗
Sorry.
是
But I'm here for the murder case.
我是为孟家凶杀案来的
[I discovered that]
我查到
[you're]
石小姐是
[Meng Duoci's French teacher.]
孟多慈小姐的法文老师
[I thought]
我想
[you might be]
或许您
even more concerned about her safety
比我更关心孟多慈小姐
than I am.
现在的安危吧
I need to buy something
我现在要去路对面
across the street.
买点东西
If necessary,
如果实在要谈
we can walk and talk.
就边走边说吧
[Sounds good.]
好的 好的 好的
Ms. Shi,
石小姐
why so late today?
今天怎么这么晚才来呀
Just finished up.
刚忙完
Are these flowers fresh?
这些花都是新鲜的吗
Yes, arrived this afternoon.
对呀 都是下午刚到的
Take your pick.
您挑挑
Ms. Shi,
石小姐您看看
do you recognize the person
照片里的这个人
in this photo?
您认识吗
No.
不认识
Has anyone from
那孟家的人
the Mengs...
有没有提到过
Are they also new today?
这个花也是今天刚到的
[Yes, you can take some.]
对 您可以带两枝
Has anyone from the Mengs
那孟家有没有人
mentioned him?
提到过他
His name is Hua Zhen.
他叫华桢
Take a look.
您看看
Mr. and Mrs. Meng
孟先生和孟太太
have so many friends.
朋友这么多
I can't possibly keep track of them all.
我不可能都留意
Is he involved in the murder case?
他和这桩凶杀案有关吗
Not exactly.
那倒也没有
I just heard
我只是听人说
he might be
这个人很有可能
harboring Duoci.
会收留多慈
As her teacher,
您是多慈的老师嘛
I thought
我想
you might know more than I do.
您了解的应该比我要多
I haven't heard anything.
反正我没有听过
Does your detective team
你们现在侦查队
also handle missing persons?
还要管人口失踪啊
It's not that.
那倒也不是
I'll take this.
就它了
Just the network of friends
关系网嘛
helping each other out.
朋友互相相托
A friend from the police station
警察局的朋友
asked me to inquire.
托我问一问
Captain Wei,
魏队长
which one do you think
你帮我看一下
is better for tying my flowers?
哪个更适合我的花呀
To match your elegance,
以石小姐的气质我认为
this one suits you best.
这个最配你
Good.
那就它了
[Ms. Shi,]
石小姐
[your flowers are ready.]
您的花好了
Oh, I can do it.
来 我来
You're not planning
你该不会是
to suffocate my flowers
准备把我的鲜花
in the trunk, are you?
闷在后备箱里吧
Not at all.
不会
No need.
也不用啊
It's amazing
没想到石小姐
to spray perfume
喜欢在后备箱里
in the trunk.
喷香水儿
So strong,
太香了
You may not understand
看来魏队长你不了解
a woman's obsession with flowers and perfume.
女人对花和香水的痴迷
Sorry,
不好意思
I couldn't be more helpful.
我这次没有帮上忙
I'm also very worried about Duoci.
我也很担心多慈
So please have your police friends
那就麻烦你的警察朋友
find her soon.
尽快找到她
Hopefully.
但愿吧
Thank you.
谢谢
Goodbye.
再见
I won't bother you further today.
今天不打扰了
Good news!
宣布一个好消息
The Police Service of the Council
公董局警务处
has dropped the complaint against us.
取消了对咱们的投诉
[The disciplinary actions]
四所的处分
[cancelled!]
没了
[Gorgeous!]
太好了
Don't get
别一个个的
too excited just yet.
高兴得太早啊
Each of you must copy
罚你们每个人抄十遍
the extradition treaty ten times!
租界的引渡条约
Also,
还有
no police officer
上面说了
in our jurisdiction
以后辖区内
is allowed to
不准出现
act above the law from now on.
目无法纪的警员
Got it?
都明白吗
Yes, sir!
明白
The perfect resolution
这次这个事件的
of this incident does
完美解决
owe a little
我老左
to me.
有小小的一点点功劳
But
当然了
the main credit
最主要的功劳
goes to our Captain Chen!
还是我们陈浩队长的
It was his
正是因为
earnest guidance,
陈队长的谆谆教导
upright integrity,
凛然正气
and virtue that...
以德服人
Why are you pulling me?
你拉我干什么
Embarrassed?
不好意思了你
Your face is all red.
脸都红了
Where was I?
我说哪儿了
His virtue.
以德服人
Right, because of his virtue,
正因为他的以德服人
he negotiated
和那个女督察员
with the female inspector
进行了谈判
and successfully
并成功地
deterred her!
震慑住了她
Let's give him
让我们用最热烈的掌声
the loudest applause to show
对陈队长表示最崇高的
our respect!
敬意
Alright! Dismissed!
好 解散
[What's for lunch?]
中午吃什么
[What's your idea?]
想吃什么
I like stir-fried beef with carrots.
我想吃胡萝卜炒牛肉
[No problem.]
行 今儿高兴
[I'll cook it for you.]
给你露一手
Close the door.
关门
Can we get the suspect back
现在可以找分局
from the precinct now?
把嫌疑人要回来了吧
Of course.
当然
Hello,
喂 你好
this is Captain Chen
这里是第四警察所
from the Fourth Station House.
我是队长陈浩
My suspect...
我的嫌疑人
When?
什么时候
Where?
在什么地方
Hello?
喂
What's wrong?
怎么了
He ran away.
背带裤跑了
Who said that?
谁说的
Wang Yong
冯广云身边
working for Feng Guangyun.
那个叫王永的说的
He said the guy
他说背带裤
jumped out of the transport vehicle
被他们带走的当天
the day they took him away
跳车逃跑了
and hasn't been found since.
到现在都没找到
How could he possibly escape
分局那么多警察
from so many police officers?
就能让他这么跑了
That's what Wang Yong said.
那个叫王永的说的
That day when we're questioning...
那天在审背带裤的时候
He's rummaging
我看他
around in the room
好像在翻箱倒柜
for something.
找什么东西
[But I was the first one]
可是是我第一个
[to rush in.]
赶进去的
[The room was neat,]
房间里面很整齐
No signs of anything being rifled through.
没有任何被翻动的痕迹
So,
也就是说
the killer may be
凶手应该是
looking for something.
在找某个东西
And he restored everything before leaving.
所以离开前还原了
Possibly.
有可能
Now that we have no eyewitness,
现在没了目击证人
we definitely won't get a sketch.
画像肯定是没有了
The case has been
这个案子已经
handed over to the precinct,
上交给了分局
we won't get any new leads.
四所不会再有新的线索
What's your plan?
你怎么打算
I'll think of another way.
我会再想别的办法
Yuansheng,
向警官
I once asked you
我之前问过你
why you're so determined
为什么一定要查
in the murder case.
孟家凶杀案
You said, that's for an honour.
你说是为了立功
[You have lots of other choices,]
能立功的案子多了
[why this one?]
为什么一定是这一个
A kid hired me
有一个小孩儿
with a string of beads
用一串项链
and 23 silver dollars
和二十三块钱
to solve her case,
雇我帮她查案
and I agreed.
我答应了
That's the truth,
这是实话
but do you believe it?
但你相信吗
Yes.
我相信
If I were you,
如果换作是我
I'd do the same.
我也会答应
[Waiter, a glass of water!]
伙计 倒杯水
Yes, sir.
来了 来了
It's your turn.
你的
You're a bit slow today.
这反应慢半拍
Right.
是
We're all waiting.
就等你了
Feeling a bit sleepy, huh?
有点儿小困是吧
Here you go.
来 大哥 水
[Come on.]
来来来
[No, thanks.]
不用 不用
You gave me
让你倒水
such a hot cup of water.
你给我倒杯开水
What were you thinking?
你想烫死我啊
Sorry.
对不起 大哥
I'm... really sorry.
对 对不起 对不起
What else
除了这句
can you say?
你还能说什么啊
No wonder
我说今天晚上
I had bad luck today.
这牌这么背呢
It's all because of you!
原来全是你方的啊
[Guys!]
伙计们 伙计们
[The boss is calling!]
老板叫了
Calm down. Let's continue.
来来来 打牌了
Get lost!
滚滚滚
[Tianxiang!]
天祥 天祥
[Hurry up!]
来 快点儿天祥
[Enough.]
行了 行了
[Get back.]
快快 打打 打你的
Send this photo out.
这照片发下去
[Someone is offering]
有人要找照片上的
[100 silver dollars]
这个小女孩儿
for this little girl in the picture.
开价一百块
My goodness.
乖乖
[That much!]
这么多
[If we find her,]
哥 这我们找着
[split it fifty-fifty.]
五五分哪
[That much money,]
这么多钱
[what kind of trouble]
这小女孩是
[is the girl in?]
惹了多大的麻烦哪
This is my big brother.
这是我哥哥骆天祥
And this is Mr. Xiang.
这是向警官
Nice to meet you.
向警官
Alright,
好了
I'll take you upstairs, okay?
我带你上去好不好
Wait here for me.
你在这儿等我吧
[In your spare time,]
闲的时候啊
[look around properly,]
四处好好地找找
[make some extra cash,]
看一看啊
help out the family.
赚点儿闲钱贴补家用
[Sounds cool.]
是是是 知道了
[Boss, what will happen]
老板 这些人要是
[after this girl]
找到这个小姑娘
[is found?]
会怎么处置她
Cut the crap.
就你话多
This is easy money.
这是闲钱
Try your best.
能挣就挣点儿
Don't care about too much.
其他的别问
[You okay?]
照片都收好了
[Yes.]
收好了
Go back to work.
来 都散了吧
Tianxiang.
哥
I've brought back
你这衣服
your laundry.
我给你收回来了
Minmin,
珉敏
are you familiar with
你跟向警官的妹妹
Mr. Xiang's sister?
熟悉吗
Not really.
不熟
I've only seen her once.
我第一次见
She has a tough life.
就身世比较可怜
She seems to
我看她还挺喜欢
really like you though.
你这哥哥的
She eats
你做的饭
everything you cook with such gusto.
她都是大口大口吃的
Really?
是吗
All set.
收好了
Good night.
你早点儿休息
[Is it salty?]
咸不咸
Not at all!
不咸 好吃
[That's good.]
不咸就行
[You like the food]
你喜欢吃
[my brother cook?]
我哥哥做的菜呀
I do!
喜欢
Director An,
安处长
may I ask
我可不可以向您
you something?
打听一件事儿
Go ahead.
你说
I heard...
我听说
Undersecretary Hua's son,
军政部华次长的儿子
from
华桢
a regular class
跟您一样
of the Army University
是陆大
like you, right?
正则班的学员对吧
Are you familiar with each other?
你们俩熟悉吗
Of course.
熟悉啊
We're classmates.
那是我老同学
Do you know
那你知不知道
if he had any contact with Communists
那他在学校的时候
when he's at school?
有没有跟赤色分子联系
The Chairman Jiang
当年蒋委员长
used to work with Zhou Enlai.
跟周恩来也共事过
What do you want to ask?
魏队长你是想问什么
I'm just particular curious.
我就是特别特别地好奇
I heard that he's
我听说他是
a top student.
陆大的优等生
Why did he change his career
为什么中途改行
to join the Navy?
去当海军了呢
It is so confusing.
这让人太费解了
I understand.
我听明白了
You think it's because of Deng Mingyuan?
你觉得是因为邓铭远
Maybe I'm too obsessed
也许是我查他
with investigating him.
查得太入迷了
Hua Zhen should have come to Shanghai.
我听说他来上海了
Back to Nanjing long ago.
早都回南京了
I sent him to the railway station myself.
我亲自送他去的火车站
When he was in Shanghai,
那他在上海的时候
did he ask you
有没有向你打听过什么
about Deng Mingyuan,
比如说他打听邓铭远
or people and things
打听和邓铭远
related to him?
相关的人或事
We're just talking about
我们之间呢无非就是
our past at school.
老同学叙叙旧
But as for the specific content,
但是至于叙的什么旧啊
I can't tell you.
那不能告诉你
Actually, I went to ask the conductor
您说的那辆火车呀
of the train you just mentioned.
我去询问了它的乘务长
He said that Hua Zhen
他说华桢当天
didn't get on the train that day
根本就没有上车
but quietly stayed in Shanghai.
悄悄地留在了上海
[He neither told you]
他没有告诉您
nor contacted anyone.
也没有联系任何人
The thread of the witness is broken.
目击证人的线索断了
We have to think of
我们现在只能想
other ways now.
其他的方法
Chen Hao and I suspect that
我和陈浩怀疑
the killer wanna get something
凶手想要去你们家
from your family.
找某样东西
[Maybe we can take advantage of this]
也许可以利用这个方法
[to entice him out.]
把他给引出来
It's just speculation.
虽然只是推测
But we don't have any other clues,
但我们没有其他的线索
so we have to try it this way.
只能用这个方法试一试
Are you going there alone?
你一个人去那儿吗
Yes.
对
I'll go to your house this afternoon,
我下午去趟你家
and see if I can figure out
看看能不能弄清楚
what the killer is looking for.
凶手究竟在找什么
You wait for me at home.
你在家里等我回来
The newspaper
远生哥哥
said that
我看见报纸上说
the memorial service
今天下午
for my parents
有人会在我家门口
will be held this afternoon.
给爸爸妈妈举行追思会
You wanna go back?
你想回去
May I?
我能去吗
It's too dangerous.
这太危险了
I just wanna go home and have a look.
我就想回家看一看
I won't go anywhere
我就躲在屋子里
but in the house, okay?
哪也不去行吗
Then you must keep close to me.
那你一定要跟紧我
You can't go
不能一个人去到
out of my sight.
我看不见的地方
OK.
好
[First bow.]
一鞠躬
[Second bow.]
二鞠躬
Let's go.
走吧
Qiushi,
秋实
everything here should be like
我们来的时候什么样
it's originally when we leave.
走的时候就得是什么样
[You must temporarily forget]
你要暂时忘掉
[that this is your home.]
这个地方是你家
[We are here today]
今天我们在这里
[to mourn the death of two benevolent people.]
哀悼两位仁者之死
[Shanghai is here to mourn]
上海在这里哀悼
[the death of an industrialist.]
实业家之死
[This indefatigable man]
这位不知疲倦的实业家
[and his]
这对乐善好施的
[beloved wife]
恩爱夫妻
[experienced a life]
在同我们一起
[full of storms]
旅居在这世上的期间
[and struggles]
经历了充满风暴
[but never compromising.]
和斗争的生活
So many people present.
来这么多人
All government departments
政府各部门
send people here.
都派人来过了
How else
不然
can the Chamber of Commerce be appeased?
怎么安抚商会情绪啊
[They rest in peace.]
他们安息了
[On the day]
在他们进入坟墓的
[they're buried,]
这一天
[they walked into]
也同时步入了
[the palace of honor.]
荣誉的宫殿
[From now on,]
从今以后
[they will]
他们将和
[shine]
无数的星星一起
[above the clouds]
熠熠闪耀于
[with countless stars.]
我们上空的云层之上
[Gentlemen standing here,]
站在这里的诸位先生
[faced with such a loss...]
面对着这样一种损失
Do you know
外面这些人
all these people out there?
你都认识吗
No.
不认识
Maybe
我猜
my mom and dad's friends.
都是爸爸妈妈的朋友吧
[I thought no one]
我以为除了我自己
[remembered]
就没有人
my parents but myself.
记得爸爸妈妈了
[... can only feel seriousness]
只能充满严肃
[and sincerity.]
和诚挚
[It's not dark.]
这不是黑夜
Move to another room.
换个房间吧
[But light.]
而是光明
[It's not the end,]
这不是结束
[but the beginning.]
而是开始
[It's not nihility,]
这不是虚无
[but eternity.]
而是永恒
Isn't the target here?
这些都不是吗
Since the murderer searched Van Hwa Hotel,
既然凶手搜过文华饭店
he must have searched your home.
那他一定搜过你家
These things
这些放到明面上的东西
left behind
他没有拿走
must not be what he wants.
说明不是他想要的
[What are these?]
这些是什么啊
HSBC deposit and withdrawal receipts
是你父母在汇丰银行
left by your parents.
存取款的票根
I've been there
我跟爸爸妈妈
with my parents.
去过那家银行
They seem to
他们好像在那儿
have rented a safe there.
租了一个保险箱
Do you know where the key is?
你知道钥匙在哪吗
What?
干吗
What happened?
怎么了
Hua Zhen.
华桢
[Why are you here?]
你怎么样
Are you okay?
受伤没有啊
Xiang Yuansheng?
向远生
[How did you become a cop?]
你怎么变成警察了
Didn't you go back to Nanjing?
你不是早都回南京了吗
What happened?
这怎么回事儿啊
And who is that man?
还有刚刚那个人又是谁
An Yin,
安殷
I'll explain everything to you
等事情处理完
when I'm done.
我会给你解释清楚的
You're
远生哥哥
injured.
你受伤了
Drinking more milk is good for you.
多喝点牛奶伤口长得快
Thank you.
谢谢
The man is looking for me,
他找的是我
not money
不是钱
or anything else, right?
或者别的什么东西吗
His attention
凶手的注意力
was on every girl
在每一个跟你相似的
who looks like you.
女孩儿身上
Therefore,
从这点来看
you're his target.
他去孟家是为了找你
He even wanna kill me?
他想连我也杀掉
After the murder
文华饭店
at Van Hwa Hotel,
凶手行凶之后
his's first looking for something
第一件事是找东西
rather than you,
而不是找你
indicating that his real purpose
说明他真正的目的
is still an object.
还是东西
But he thinks
但他觉得
he can find it
可以通过你
through you.
找到那样东西
But I don't know anything.
可我什么都不知道啊
Remember HSBC
记得我跟你说过的
I mentioned?
汇丰银行吧
Maybe you can be useful to him.
也许你对他真的有用
Mr. Meng
孟先生
did keep
确实在这里租用了
the safety box in our bank.
私人保险箱
But in order to open it,
如果要取走他的遗物
you have to present
需要出示合法的
the death certificate and the key, please.
死亡证明以及钥匙
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
The key has been lost.
钥匙已经遗失了
Is there any other way for me
我还有其他办法
to open the safe?
打开保险箱吗
Only his direct relatives
那只有他的直系亲属
can open the safe,
有权利打开箱子
like his children.
比如子女
Okay.
好的
[Newspaper!]
卖报 卖报
[Is that all the information]
您的寻人启事
[of your search notice?]
就这些内容吗
Yeah.
对
They must be immediately published.
但我需要尽快见报
No problem,
可以是可以
but
但是
you have to charge a third more.
得多收三分之一价钱
[How about a headline?]
要不来个头版头条
Or double the font
或者像这样
like this?
把字体再加粗一倍
But that would add
不过那样价钱
another third to the price.
就得再多收三分之一了
No,
不用了
I just need
我只需要一份
a notice
看起来很正常的
that looks normal.
寻人启事
[OK.]
行
[I will publish it now.]
那我现在就给您登报
Thank you.
谢谢
Hey, come here.
你过来 来
You weren't notified
分局也没通知
for a meeting.
你们警察所过来开会呀
I'm here to deliver something.
我来送东西的
To whom?
送给谁呀
Mr. Feng.
冯科长
Hold on,
那你等会儿啊
I'll go in and inform.
我进去通报
Wait.
你等会儿
Do you think Mr. Feng
你觉得这种事情
would want others to know?
冯科长会想让人知道吗
I'll slip in and out.
我悄悄进去 悄悄出来
Go ahead.
去吧
Thanks.
多谢
Hurry up.
抓紧啊
The case is closed.
结案了
How is that possible?
怎么可能
[Who's there?]
谁在档案室里面
It's so late.
这大晚上的
How can anyone be here?
怎么会有人啊
I seem to
我好像看到
see light inside.
门缝里边有光
Look over there.
你往那边看看
You must see things in a blur.
我说你啊一定是眼花了
Who can be here
这大晚上的
at such late night?
谁来档案室
Let's go.
赶紧走吧
Hurry up.
走了
Go.
走
What's up?
怎么了
I...
远生哥哥
don't wanna see you continue investigating.
我不想让你再查下去了
Why?
为什么
You've got injured
你为了帮我抓凶手
for catching the killer.
都受伤了
I don't want
远生哥哥
to see
我不想看到你
such a thing happen.
为我受到伤害
I can hide
我自己一个人
in Shanghai alone.
在上海躲着
You go back to Nanjing.
你回南京吧
You exchanged everything
你拿你所有的东西
for me to work for you
雇了我一个月
for a month, didn't you?
不记得了吗
Forget it.
那些东西我不要了
I keep my word
我答应帮你找到凶手
not only for you,
不光是对你的承诺
but for the man
也是对那个
who asked me to come to Shanghai.
托我来上海送小说的人
Besides,
再说了
we have a clue now, haven't we?
现在不也有线索了吗
You mean the safe?
你是说银行的保险箱
Right.
对
You're the key.
你就是那把钥匙
That's why the killer
这也是凶手
has been looking for you.
一直在找你的原因
Let's sneak into the bank
那我们偷偷去银行
and take the things away.
把里面的东西取出来呗
This is not a solution.
这解决不了问题啊
The killer knows
凶手知道
you are the key,
只有你能把东西取走
so he won't give up searching for you.
他就不会放弃找你
I do have a plan
我倒是有一个计划
that might draw him out,
也许能把他引出来
but it requires
但是需要提前
some preparation.
做一些准备
Go to bed.
快去睡觉吧
Are you leaving the Fourth Station?
你要离开四所吗
I've already
该查的线索
obtained what I want.
都已经查到了
There is no need for me
我也没有必要
to stay there any longer.
继续留在那儿了